Okay, so let's talk about the other
component of emotional intelligence then,
which is interpersonal skills.
I remember, interpersonal skills is
basically how well you build relationship
with others, and how well you understand
the other's point of view.
Now, when it comes to interpersonal
skills, right, though, the interpersonal
skills section of emotional intelligence,
there are two basic components.
There's empathy and social skills.
Right.
So let's talk about empathy first.
Now, empathy refers to how well you relate
to others.
How well do you relate to other people?
How well do you understand their point of
view, right?
It's to recognize everybody's different.
Everyone's had different experiences in
life.
So understanding these different
experiences, right, Walking in somebody
else's shoes, that's really what empathy
refers to.
Understanding somebody else's viewpoint.
So you have had your experiences.
You've had experiences in life.
Those experiences in life have basically
gotten you to where you are right now.
Well, so have others as well.
Everybody's had their experiences.
Some have had challenging experiences.
Some have had, you know, not so
challenging experiences.
everyone's had their own difficulties and
different types of difficulties and so and
so forth to get to where they are at right
now.
And empathy is understanding that,
understanding that point of view,
or rather understanding others' point of
view, recognizing that people have
different experiences,
recognizing that people
have come a long way
to where they are at today.
Like I said, it's understanding the
other's point of view.
So these are the different components then
of empathy.
So the first one then, understanding
others, right?
Observing emotional cues, appreciating
other people's point of view.
That is understanding others, listening,
observing, serving others based on their
needs, and then adjusting your own
behavior accordingly.
So again, people are going to see your
behavior.
Right, people are going to see how you
behave.
But do you understand how you behave?
So that was the personal skills.
Now we're talking about interpersonal
skills, recognizing the other person, right?
Looking at the other way around now.
So understanding, observing their cues,
and then adjusting your behavior according
to, you know, adjusting your behavior
according to their emotions.
Then another part of, Another component of
empathy is service orientation,
basically recognizing the needs of others.
I'm basically providing
assistance if needed,
understanding the
customer's point of view.
It's not just about what we're going to
deliver.
It's always also about
understanding, well, what
the customer, what does
a customer really want?
Again, it's not, oh, this is easier for
us, so let's deliver what's easy for us.
Doing this piece of work is far,
easy for us to do, right?
So let's deliver this, right?
But what does a customer really want?
So again, let's say when
you're building a house,
right, you want a wall in
one particular area, right?
But the builder's
saying, no, let's just put
it in this area because
it's a lot easy to do.
We'll move the wall by, you know,
six inches or we'll move it by,
you know, foot or whatever it is and
because it's easier for us.
Well, is that really what the customer
wanted?
Right.
So it's then, understanding
what the customer
wants, understanding the
customer's point of view.
And then part of empathy is also
developing others.
A leader will always, always develop
others.
And that's part of leadership,
recognizing and rewarding achievement,
right, and then coaching and mentoring.
So remember, a leader will say,
what do you think we should do?
Why do think we should do that?
A manager is more delegating.
A manager will say, you do this,
you do this, you do this, whereas a leader
will be saying, well, what do you think we
should do?
Why do we think, why do you think we
should do that?
That is all part of developing,
right?
It's developing others.
So a leader will also develop others to
become a leader as well.
Part of leadership then is also leveraging
diversity, part of empathy,
leveraging diversity.
Appreciating differences, appreciating
that there's different people of different
ideas, not discriminating in any way,
objecting to any kind of discrimination,
bigotry and so and so forth, in any way,
because leveraging diversity, appreciating
differences then moves over into political
awareness as well.
And, you know, showing consideration for
diverse groups and understanding political
differences, personal differences,
and so on and so forth.
Bring in everything together.
So again, empathy is about
walking in somebody else's shoes,
recognizing the differences
between all different groups.
Now, another component then of
interpersonal skills is social skills.
And social skills then
basically is how well
you build relationship with other people.
Naturally, how well you build
relationship.
Because remember, again, Again,
a leader is a communicator.
A leader is someone that networks.
A leader is someone
that builds trust amongst
others and build bonds amongst others.
And so part of social skills then,
number one skill is communication.
That is the number one skill for a project
manager.
That is the one number one skill for a
leader.
Again, think about this.
How many leaders do you know that don't
know how to communicate?
a leader has to communicate.
These first three items here, I mean,
is absolutely vital for a leader.
Communication, building bonds,
collaboration.
So communication, effectively communicating,
ensuring communication is clear.
Part of communication is bringing,
you know, building trust.
Part of emotional intelligence is to build
trust amongst others.
And the way to build trust is by
communication.
Part of emotional intelligence,
a good leader, right?
We'll be networking, building bonds,
right?
Mutually beneficial relationships.
And how?
By communicating.
And how do you build bonds also?
By collaborating.
Collaborating in cooperation.
Fostering a collaborative environment.
People are working together.
These are absolutely vital for a good
leader.
So, and that's all part of emotional
intelligence.
right.
Again, a good leader will be a good
communicator.
A good leader is someone that can network
or whether it's a good or bad leader.
Again, I'm not advocating who's a good
leader or a bad leader, right,
but any kind of leader, they can
communicate to the audience.
Right, they can communicate to their
workers.
Right.
So, and part of that is also networking,
fostering collaboration
and so on and so forth.
They're also a change catalyst.
They're an advocate for change.
They embrace change.
So remember, as I've mentioned before,
when we're talking about self-regulation,
right, we're talking about innovation in
the self-regulation element.
By definition, a project is a change.
A product is one of the
definitions of a project, temporary
endeavor undertaken to create
a unique product service or result.
It's unique, it's different.
And therefore, by definition, it's a
change.
So a project manager will always be
advocating change.
And then part of this send is also going
to be conflict management, right,
part of your social skills.
Conflict management, there's going to be
conflicts, right?
There's a whole video on conflict
management.
In fact, there's a couple of videos in
conflict management.
You're going to be managing conflict,
right?
Influencing, you have influencing skills.
You want to encourage, right?
How do you build bonds and collaborate by
influencing?
And you're influencing
stakeholders, encouraging
stakeholders to make the
best decision for your project.
and of course leadership team capabilities
developing the team right part of your
interpersonal skills part of social skills
is also developing right developing others
these are all the different components
then of emotional intelligence